Guide to the New-York Historical Society John Watts DePeyster Publication Fund Records 1857-1982 NYHS-RG 10
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society John Watts DePeyster Publication Fund records
1857-1982
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 10
17.75 Linear feet in 30 document boxes, 11 volumes, and three boxes of various sizes holding ledgers, checks, and index cards
The New-York Historical Society's Publication Fund was formed in 1858 to provide the financial means of publishing annual volumes of N-YHS's Collections. Taking the name John Watts DePeyster Publication Fund in 1908, the Fund was used to produce 85 volumes from 1868 to 1975. These volumes were distributed to Fund shareholders and to other institutions in exchanges of publications. This record group primarily includes the registers, correspondence, and other records concerning shareholder administration, such as certificate purchases and transfers of ownership, and publication distribution. The record group also includes the offering circulars, subscription book, certificate books, some nineteenth century financial records, and other documents.
Arrangement Note
The record group is organized in two series:
Series I. Transaction Records
Series II. Correspondence
Biographical/Historical Note
Within just a few years of its founding in 1804, the New-York Historical Society began publication of a series of books titled Collections of the New-York Historical Society. There were at least two purposes to this: the dissemination of the content of important historical source materials and the preservation of this content in the event of the loss of the original documents. Five volumes of what came to be known as the First Series of the Collections appeared between 1811 and 1830. After a decade, publication of the Collections began again in 1841, restarting with Volume I of a Second Series. Four volumes of this Second Series were published, with the last appearing in 1859.
Yet, as noted in a retrospective review conducted in 1882 by a Committee on Publications for the N-YHS Executive Committee, the costs of producing the First and Second Series of the Collections commonly resulted in financial hardship and risks to N-YHS and to publication subscribers. Accordingly, a new funding plan for the Collections had been sought. On April 13, 1858, Librarian George H. Moore proposed to the N-YHS Executive Committee that a Publication Fund be established to provide for the regular publication of the Collections. A special committee consisting of Moore, George Folsom and Erastus C. Benedict was formed to consider the proposal. The three reported back to the Executive Committee on May 18, 1858 with a specific plan that was endorsed by the Committee, and the proposed Publication Fund was then approved by the Society at its meeting of the same date. Immediately thereafter, on June 1, 1858, a circular was distributed soliciting subscriptions to the Fund.
As described in the circular, the Publication Fund would issue 1,000 shares at $25 per share. The monies would be invested, with the income used to publish N-YHS's transactions and Collections in American History. Holders of the shares were entitled to a copy of each and every volume issued by the Fund, which had the objective of publishing one volume annually. The number of each annual volume to be printed was to be capped at 1,250; 1,000 of these were for distribution to the shareholders and the remainder were for the N-YHS library and for exchange with other institutions. Recognizing that it would take time to sell all the shares and build enough principal and income to start publishing, the Fund proposed to pay a dividend of 5% on their principal to shareholders until publications commenced.
The Fund did not get off to a strong start. By early 1860, when sales largely ceased, only about 100 of the 1,000 shares had been sold. In 1864, with publications not yet started, the Fund made its first cash dividend payment to the shareholders. This was followed by a renewed sales effort in April 1865, which proved to be more successful. By 1866, about 750 of the 1,000 shares had been sold. Sales again largely plateaued at this point but, though short of the capital target, the decision was made to initiate publishing. In 1868, the second and last cash dividend was paid to shareholders, as Volume I of the Publication Fund Series of the Collections was also issued that year.
Sales of the shares continued after 1866, but never reached the 1,000 available. By 1900, about 811 shares had been sold. The last sale of an original share—number 850—occurred in 1930. Most of the shares were bought by individuals, with James Lenox purchasing the first ten certificates in 1858. Libraries and other institutions also purchased shares. Further, the shares could be sold, bequeathed, or otherwise transferred. New certificates numbered from 1,001 were issued to the transferees; the final certificate number issued was 1,558 in 1979. Many of the original and transferred certificates were handed down to other individuals, though many were also donated or bequeathed to institutions. For example, historian George Bancroft's share (#15) was given to the New York Public Library, as were several owned by James Lenox.
But many purchased certificates eventually went unused. When volumes were published, notice was sent to the shareholders of record that they could claim the volume at N-YHS or provide a stated amount of postage for the book to be shipped. As the decades passed, many volumes went unclaimed, piling up in the thousands in storage at N-YHS. These included volumes reserved for the unsold shares, as new purchasers were given the right to acquire not just future volumes, but all earlier ones as well. By the 1920s, steps were taken to both trim the print run to a realistic number below 1,250 and to drop about 300 names from the rolls based on the extended lack of communication and claims from them.
Starting from its earliest, undercapitalized days, the Publication Fund struggled financially to maintain the pace of one volume per year. By 1882, when the Executive Committee reviewed the publication program, the pace was about four years behind. The volume issued in 1907 was for the year 1899, eight years behind. Some attempt was made to address the financial problem by raising the share price to $50 in June 1866 and to $100 in 1883, and at least two special donations totalling $1500 were made in 1907 to defray the costs of producing particular back volumes. But by the close of 1907 the Fund amounted to only $25,450, all of it paid-in capital, and N-YHS's Annual Report noted the inadequacy of this amount for generating enough income to publish all the back volumes. It was at this point, in 1908, that the Fund received a major financial boost with a bequest of almost $24,000 from John Watts DePeyster. To satisfy the condition of the bequest, the Publication Fund was renamed the John Watts DePeyster Publication Fund. The price of the shares was also increased in 1908 to $200.
DePeyster's bequest seems to have made a critical difference in the Fund's ability to publish the Collections, at least for a time. By about 1916, the Fund had caught up on its back volumes and remained roughly on pace into the 1930s. Even faced with the limits imposed by World War II, the Fund was behind by only a couple of years in the mid-1940s. Yet, costs were moving beyond what the Fund could support. In 1954, the Fund published the volume for 1948. In that same year, N-YHS Director R.W.G. Vail noted that the Fund would need to be more than doubled to cover the cost of printing an annual volume. Indeed, the next volume, for 1949, was not published until 1965. The final three volumes (Vols. 83-85 for 1950-1952) were published by the Fund in the 1970s, the last in 1975. In the 1990s, as part of the overall financial reorganization that took place then at N-YHS, the role of the DePeyster Publication Fund as the source of funding for the series of Collections, and the series itself, ended. The remnant of the Fund remains as a source for select initiatives, such as its co-sponsorship in 1998 of Helena Zinkham's A Guide to Print, Photograph, Architecture & Ephemera Collections.
(Principal sources for this note, other than the Publication Fund records themselves, include R.W.G. Vail's Knickerbocker Birthday, Executive Committee minute books and papers found in the New-York Historical Society management committee records (NYHS-RG 1), and the N-YHS Annual Reports, especially those for 1907 and 1908. Vail's book includes a comprehensive list of the contents of all volumes of all three series of the Collections, through 1954, on pages 491-501.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Most of the materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives). Other record groups that are processed and available to researchers and are especially related to the New-York Historical Society John Watts DePeyster Publication Fund (NYHS-RG 10) are as follows:
Abstracts made in the 1920s from the Executive Committee and N-YHS minute books of entries related to the DePeyster Publication Fund, and from the so-called "official papers" associated with these, are found in Series I of this record group. The original minutes and at least some of the official papers (some of the abstracted papers could not be found in 2015) can be found in the New-York Historical Society management committee records (NYHS-RG 1).
The New-York Historical Society general correspondence record group (NYHS-RG 2) contains documents relating to the Publication Fund, including inquiries on purchases, transfers, orders, withdrawals, and other shareholder matters. These materials begin appearing around 1885.
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society John Watts DePeyster Publication Fund record group primarily includes the records concerning the Fund's shareholders. These records include the registers and other documents recording share purchases and transfers, the deliveries of the published volumes, and the cash dividends paid to early shareholders in the 1860s. The records also include correspondence concerning purchases, transfers, orders, exchanges with other institutions, and other administrative activities. The record group includes some foundational documents, such as the 1858 report of the committee that recommended the formation of the Fund, the circular soliciting subscriptions, subscription book, and certificate book. There are early financial records from the nineteenth century, including bank books, bills, cancelled checks, notes on investments and revenue, and the like.
The documents in this record group center on shareholder administration and publication distribution. The record group does not include any documents concerning the editorial process, content choices, or other aspects of producing the Collections. Also, the documents relate exclusively to the volumes published through the Publication Fund and, aside from occasional other references in the correspondence, do not concern other N-YHS publications, such as the Proceedings or works published as part of the John Divine Jones Fund series.
New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Associations, institutions, etc. -- Publishing -- New York (State) -- New York; Libraries -- Publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Museums -- Publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Checks (bank checks); Financial records.; Invoices.; Letters (correspondence); Lists (document genres); Registers (lists); Subscription lists; New-York Historical Society -- Archives.; New-York Historical Society -- Publishing.; New-York Historical Society. John Watts De Peyster Publication Fund; New-York Historical Society. Publication Fund
- Series I. Transaction Records, 1858-1982; 5.63 Linear feet
  Arrangement Note
  The Transaction Records series is arranged by format and in rough chronological order. The series opens with the foundational documents of the Publication Fund, such as offering circulars, and records related to the initial acquisition of shareholders, such as the subscription and certificate books. These are followed by early financial records, such as documents related to dividends paid, bank books, and Fund expenditures. These are followed by the registers and other records recording shareholder activity, such as purchases and transfers, and the various documents recording deliveries and exchanges of volumes.
  Scope and Contents Note
  The Transaction Records series includes those documents recording various activities of the Publication Fund, especially the issuance of Fund certificates, the payment of dividends in the years prior to the start of publishing, the delivery of publications, and some nineteenth century expenditures. The bulk of the series includes several volumes, including the two original share certificate books in which stubs remain for the issued shares with the name of the investor and later transfer information, as well as unused blank certificates. One of these certificate books dates from the Fund's beginning in 1858; the other dates from 1908 and includes certificates bearing the new reference to DePeyster in its title.
  Other volumes include subscriber names and addresses, publications delivered to them, dividends due and paid, and exchanges of publications with other institutions. In addition to the registers, records about the changes in share ownership over time are found in card files and various informal lists, especially one from 1944 that seemed to result from a significant effort to reconcile and update the shareholder records. The series includes some documents dating from the founding of the Fund, including the report of the committee that recommended the creation of the Fund, the 1858 and 1865 offering circulars, a subscription book, and other early material. Transcriptions from the 1920s of relevant nineteenth century minutes and reports are in the series. Financial records date from the nineteenth century and include bank books, cancelled checks, dividend payment records, bills, and notes on investment income.
  - Reports and Resolutions (1 of 2), 1858-1870s(?) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Includes the report of the Special Committee of the Executive Committee formed to consider the proposal for a Publication Fund (1858), minutes of the Publication Fund Committee meeting of June 9, 1866, and other early documents.
  - Reports and Resolutions (2 of 2), 1921, 1925, 1944, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Includes abstracts prepared in the 1920s and 1940s of Executive Committee and Society meetings pertinent to the Fund (1858-1925) and legal opinions from the 1920s concerning the quantities of each volume to be published, stored, and other related questions.
  - Offering Circular, 1858 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Circular to Members, 1860 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Includes the circular sent to members providing information about N-YHS meetings, galleries, and other features, including the Publication Fund.
  - Offering Circular, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Publication Fund Certificates, 1858-1908 (Volume RG10.1)
    Includes the stubs for original, sold certificates #1 through 832; unsold certificates 833 through 1000; and the stubs for certificates #1001 through 1338 obtained by transfer.
  - John Watts DePeyster Publishing Fund Certificates, 1908-1979 (Volume RG10.2)
    Includes the stubs for original, sold certificates #833 through 850; the stubs for certificates #1339 through 1558 obtained by transfer; and blank, unused certificates.
  - Subscription Forms and Certificates, 1858, 1865, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Includes subscription request forms and loose, blank certificates.
  - Original Subscription Book, 1858-1860 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Subscription Notes and Lists, circa 1860-1869 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Names of Subscribers (Printed Lists), 1865, 1868-1870 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lists of Subscribers and Dividends Due, 1860-1871 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Publication Fund Dividends, 1864, 1868 (Volume RG10.3)
    Includes the recipients and amounts paid for the first and second dividends from the Fund.
  - Dividend Payment Transmittal Forms, 1864, 1869 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Dividend Payments. Cancelled Checks, 1864, 1868 (Box 1)
  - Bank of America. Publication Fund Bank Book, 1859-1884 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Includes a record of Fund purchases, income and expenses.
  - Bank of America. Publication Fund Bank Books (3), 1859-1883 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Abstract of Account, 1859-1877 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Includes a summary of income and expenses for the Fund for the date range.
  - Fund Income, 1860s, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Includes 1907 correspondence related to donations from Archer Milton Huntington and Samuel V. Hoffman to the Fund.
  - Fund Expenditures (1 of 2), 1860-1884 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Includes the Fund's cancelled checks for investments and expenses for 1860-1884 (the bills related to these checks are in this folder and the next), a summary of expenses for 1867-1890, and bills from the 1860s.
  - Fund Expenditures (2 of 2), 1870-1896 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Publication Fund Ledger (Original Book), 1859-circa 1966 (Box 2)
    This is the register of what appears to be the original entries of shareholder accounts (i.e., purchases, transfers, publications offered, etc.).
  - Publication Fund Ledger (New Book), [1944]-circa 1978 (Volume RG10.4)
    This register appears to have been initiated in 1944 by purging obsolete names from the "original book" and carrying forward only current shareholders. (See shareholder list as of 1944 below.) Active accounts transcribed from the original book date back to the 19th century; new entries span to about 1978.
  - Publication Fund Shareholders A-Z, [1944]-circa 1979 (Box 3)
    This is a set of index cards with shareholder information in alphabetical order by name. Likely initiated in the 1940s to complement the "new book." Updates to the cards extend to about 1979.
  - Shareholder List as of 23 August 1944 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
  - Publication Fund Deliveries. Volume for 1868, 1868-1870 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
  - Publication Fund Deliveries. Volumes for 1869 and 1870, 1870-1873 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
  - Publication Fund Deliveries. Volumes for 1868-1872. Memorandum, circa 1869-1873 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
  - [Publication Fund Deliveries], circa 1870s-1882? (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
    Includes names and addresses of shareholders with checkmarks likely referring to orders of published volumes.
  - Publication Fund Deliveries, 1880-1897? (Box 2)
  - Publication Fund Deliveries, circa 1902 (Volume RG10.5)
  - [Publication Fund Deliveries], circa 1906-1937 (Volume RG10.6)
  - Publication Fund Deliveries, 1868-1918 (Volume RG10.7)
    Includes a record of deliveries by volume.
  - Publication Fund Deliveries, 1919-1973 (Volume RG10.8)
  - Publication Fund Delivery Book, 1973-1982 (Volume RG10.9)
  - Publication Fund Exchange, circa 1910-1975 (Volume RG10.10)
    Includes a record of volumes sent to other institutions for exchange.
  - Delivery Lists Working Files (1 of 4), circa 1940? (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    This set of four folder includes lists of deliveries for the volumes of 1911-1936, with s few related notes. These appear to be working files from the late 1930s or early 1940s with the purpose of reconciling and updating records of past deliveries and current shareholders.
  - Delivery Lists Working Files (2 of 4), circa 1940? (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
  - Delivery Lists Working Files (3 of 4), circa 1940? (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
  - Delivery Lists Working Files (4 of 4), circa 1940? (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
- Series II. Correspondence, 1857-1982; 12.13 Linear feet
  The Correspondence series was kept largely in its original arrangement. Generally, this was by subject matter, but there is a great deal of overlap in content among the sections of correspondence.
  The series opens with the so-called shareholder correspondence, which includes letters about transfers, orders, and other matters; these files are arranged in shareholder number order. Files numbered 1001 and higher, which refer to certificates issued because of transfers of ownership, often hold the original shareholder's correspondence and certificate. These are followed by correspondence concerning offers of and orders for publication volumes number 15 through 61, with gaps; some of these letters also refer to transfers and matters other than orders.
  Orders are followed by two sets of files concerning exchanges of publications with other institutions. The second set is designated as "obsolete" in the container list, which was a notation on the original folders and was transcribed here. These are presumably those institutions with which exchanges were ended.
  Exchanges are followed by general (originally called "miscellaneous") correspondence folders, which are arranged chronologically, and also concern orders, exchanges, and other shareholder matters as above. In addition to the folders of letters, the general correspondence files include one album of letters.
  The Correspondence series primarily includes letters to and from the Fund shareholders concerning announcements of published volumes, orders for the volumes, transfers of shares, and other shareholder matters. There are many letters from the original share purchasers of 1858-1866 transmitting their $25 payments, as well as the original certificates that were returned to N-YHS over time for transfer and issuance of new certificates to transferees. The correspondence also includes letters to and from institutions concerning exchanges of publications. A small amount of the correspondence refers to Proceedings and other N-YHS publications that were not part of the Publication Fund program.
  - Shareholders #11-110 (5 folders), 1857-1981 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10-14)
  - Shareholders #112-390 (11 folders), 1865-1978 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-11)
  - Shareholders #397-679 (11 folders), 1865-1978 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-11)
  - Shareholders #681-850 (8 folders), 1866-1979 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-8)
  - Shareholders #1001-1124 (7 folders), 1858-1978 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-7)
  - Shareholders #1125-1250 (7 folders), 1859-1978 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-7)
  - Shareholders #1251-1339 (6 folders), 1858-1980 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1-6)
  - Shareholders #1341-1404 (6 folders), 1859-1978 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1-6)
  - Shareholders #1405-1461 (6 folders), 1860-1979 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1-6)
  - Shareholders #1463-1500 (5 folders), 1865-1982 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1-5)
  - Shareholders #1501-1539 (5 folders), 1865-1979 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1-5)
  - Shareholders #1540-1558 (3 folders), 1865-1979 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 1-3)
  - Orders. Volumes 15-17 (3 folders), 1888-1890 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 4-6)
  - Orders. Volumes 18, 21 (7 folders), 1891-1892, 1894 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 1-7)
  - Orders. Volume 23, 24 (8 folders), 1896-1898 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 1-8)
  - Orders. Volumes 25, 26 (8 folders), 1901-1902 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 1-8)
  - Orders. Volume 27 (5 folders), 1902 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 1-5)
  - Orders. Volume 28 (5 folders), 1903-1904 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 1-5)
  - Orders. Volume 29 (5 folders), 1904 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 1-5)